Guide to the James Stewart McDermott Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Stewart McDermott papers
1938-1945
MS 1073
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The papers consist of letters written by James Stewart McDermott to his family and friends, describing his life at Yale College and in the Marine Corps. His wartime letters were written from Quantico, Virginia; Washington, D.C; Camp Pendleton; and unspecified locations in the Pacific, until his death on Iwo Jima. The papers also include a few newspaper clippings and other items.
McDermott, James Stewart, 1921-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Katharine Stewart McDermott, 1945-1946.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The James Stewart McDermott Papers consist almost entirely of letters that McDermott wrote to his mother and sister from Yale College (1938 Sep-1942 Apr), Quantico, Virginia, and Washington, D.C. (1942 May-1944 Jan), Camp Pendleton (1944 Mar-Sep), and various unspecified locations in the Pacific (1944 Sep-1945 Feb). Besides many observations about ordinary events at Yale and in the Marine Corps, there are accounts of conversations with Maury Maverick, U.S. Representative from Texas, and James Grafton Rogers, deputy director of the Office of Strategic Services, and descriptions of social life in wartime Washington.
Biographical / Historical
James Stewart McDermott, B.A. 1942.
Born February 15, 1921, in Topeka, Kans.; Died March 2, 1945, on Iwo Jima.
Father, George Thomas McDermott (Ph.B. Univ. Chicago 1908, J.D. 1910), judge 10th Judicial Circuit, U.S. Circuit Court, Topeka; son of James and Tirzah (Henderson) McDermott of Winfield, Kans. Mother, Katharine (Stewart) McDermott (Washburn Coll. ex-'17); daughter of James Harvey and Kate (Martin) Stewart of Wichita, Kans.
Topeka High School. Scholar of the second rank Freshman and Junior years; high oration appointment Senior year; Freshman Swimming Squad; member Timothy Dwight College (football team Sophomore year; Senior aide) and Phi Beta Kappa. Member Grace Cathedral (Episcopal), Topeka. Unmarried.
Enlisted in U.S. Marine Corps Reserve March 5, 1942; enrolled in Candidates Class, Quantico, May-July, and Reserve Officers Class July 18-September 26, 1942; commissioned Second Lieutenant, Marine Corps Reserve, July 18, 1942, and Second Lieutenant, Marine Corps, September 26, 1942; promoted First Lieutenant April 12, 1943, and Captain August, 1944; at Training Center, Fleet Marine Force, Marine Barracks, New River, N.C., taking field artillery course November 19-December 8, 1942; stationed at Quantico as artillery, motor transport, and matérial [ sic] instructor until February, 1944 (rewrote a number of instruction pamphlets and wrote several instruction books for classroom use); stationed at Camp Pendleton February, 1944, until sent overseas in September, 1944; commanding officer of a battery, 13th Regiment, 5th Marine Division, stationed at a Pacific island base; took part in invasion of Iwo Jima in February, 1945.
Captain McDermott was fatally wounded while on reconnaissance on Iwo Jima. Buried in 5thMarine Division Cemetery on that island. Posthumously awarded the Navy Cross. Survived by mother, maternal grandmother, and two sisters, Jane McDermott Hergenreter (B.A. Stanford Univ. 1937), the wife of Capt. William Hergenreter, A.U.S. (B.A. Washburn Coll. 1940), and Mary Katharine McDermott Shideler (B.A. Swarthmore Coll. 1938), the wife of Rev. Emerson Wayne Shideler (B.A. Univ. Pittsburgh 1937; B.D. Chicago Theological Seminary 1940) of Russell, Kans.
(Taken from Yale University Obituary Record, 1943-45, pp. 198-199).
World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; United States -- Armed Forces -- Military Life; United States -- Politics and government; Washington (D.C.) -- Social life and customs; McDermott, James Stewart, 1921-1945; Yale University -- Student life
- Inventory
  - Letters
    - JSMcD to his mother, Katharine (Stewart) McDermott, 1938-1945 (Box 1)
    - JSMcD to his sister, Mary (McDermott) Shideler, 1939-1943 (Box 2)
    - JSMcD to family and friends, 1941-1945 (Box 2)
    - Terrell (Mrs. Maury) Maverick to Katharine (Stewart) McDermott, 1944 (Box 2)
    - James Grafton Rogers to the Commandant of the U.S. Marine Corps, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Meditation on the significance of life, undated (Box 2)
  - Navy Cross citation (photostatic copy), 1945 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1945 (Box 2)